Guide to the University Christian Movement in New England Records - Addendum A
Yale University Divinity School Library
University Christian Movement in New England Records - Addendum A
1886-2000
RG 88A
Yale University Divinity School Library
6
(14 boxes)
This addendum to the main collection of the University Christian Movement in New England Records (see Record Group 88) contains all the remaining material belonging to the organization that was not submitted to Yale University in 1998. The present collection, composed of historical documents, correspondence, reports, minutes of meetings, printed material, financial invoices, photographs, slides, an audio tape, as well as other artifacts, spans the entire history of the organization. It provides insight into college campus ministry in New England at the turn of the 20th century, and in the years between the two world wars. This small added collection also fills in many of the details of the former collection that dealt with the turbulent 1960s and 1970s, and expands its coverage of the UCMNE through the more placid 1980s and 1990s until the organization's dissolution. The University Christian Movement in New England was a non-denominational inclusive campus ministry organization headquartered for the most part in Cambridge, MA. Officially formed anew with a name change in 1967 it was a continuation of the Student Christian Movement in New England, which had been formed by the YWCA, YMCA and various other groups as an umbrella organization to promote religious co-operation on the campuses of the six states of New England.
University Christian Movement in New England
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the University Christian Movement in New England.
Biographical / Historical
The bulk of this addendum to Record Group 88 documents the University Christian Movement in New England from 1975 to 1996. The Reverend Christine Blackburn was hired as director of the UCMNE in 1978 and under her leadership the organization flourished, sponsoring Winter, Spring and Fall Conferences annually, as well as Summer workshops, on specific, relevant "hot topics" of the time. In the last quarter of the 20th century alone, UCMNE organized more than fifty major conferences, attracting students and others from around the country.
Certainly the peak of the UCMNE's "Golden Age" of activity was its 50th anniversary celebration held at First Church in Cambridge, MA, on the morning of Sunday, October 21, 1984. Planning for the event had consumed the energies of the organization for more than a year, and when the day itself arrived, hundreds of honored guests, alumni, friends, and current student members assembled to celebrate. The glow of that event seemed to energize the organization for the following decade; but by 1990s there were signs of trouble.
In April of 1996, the director, Lee Ann Hopkins, and her staff submitted a letter to the Board of Directors recommending that UCMNE be dissolved for a number of reasons: lack of student interest and involvement, the decline of liberal campus ministries, a lack of funding, and the problem of gaining access to college campuses. The Board directed that there should be a "needs assessment" taken and authorized the hiring of qualified people to do the task. Interest in the organization, however, continued to wane in spite of the efforts of Lee Ann Hopkins, who had succeeded Blackburn as director in 1993. Hopkins resigned in July, 1996, and was followed by Paige Blair who resigned only a year later. In May, 1997, Nancy Richards became the last director and valiantly attempted to re-energize the organization. For a while it seemed those efforts would succeed, but it was not to be. After sixty-six years of service to the Church, the University Christian Movement in New England came to an end, merging into the Boston-Cambridge Ministry in Higher Education. The latest documents in this collection date from 2000.
Scope and Contents
I. Organization and Policy Records, 1934-2000
II. Conferences and Events, 1942 - 1999
III. Related Organizations, 1920 - 1999
IV. Financial Matters, 1947 - 1998
V. Publications, 1976 - 1995
VI. Photographs and Slides, 1886 - 1999
VII. Artifacts, 1990 - 2000
These records add another piece to the complicated, evolving picture of Protestant religious work among college and university students in America. They complement various other collections held by the Yale Divinity Library, including the archives of the UCMNE's predecessor, the Student Christian Movement in New England, the YMCA Student Division, United Ministries in Higher Education, and personal papers of Helen Morton and Margaret Flory. Though there is overlap between this addendum and the original collection of archives found in Record Group 88, this collection fills in and adds to the story of the UCMNE in substantive ways.
Series I, Organization and Policy Records, includes historical material spanning sixty-three years, dating back to the founding of the Student Christian Movement in 1934, as well as important internal documents contained in the minutes of the meetings of the Board of Directors from 1966 to 2000. An unpublished history of the Student Christian Movement up until 1948 by Wilmer Kitchen provides valuable historical background. The "Correspondence" subseries contains letters from such notables as President Clinton, Senators Kerry and Kennedy, Newt Gingrich, and "Tip" O'Neill.
Series II, Conferences and Events, is the largest series of the collection. In the "Conferences, Sessions, Planning Meetings" subseries, detailed information from more than fifty major conferences, held from 1942 to 1999, stands as an enduring tribute to the lasting influence of UCMNE. There is extensive documentation related to the 50th anniversary celebration of the UCMNE.
Series III, Related Organizations, contains documentation related to denominational and other organizations with which the UCMNE was involved, including the Student Christian Movement of Canada, the World Student Christian Federation, and the National Ecumenical Student Conference.
Series IV, Financial Matters, contains financial and tax records, primarily from the last quarter of the 20th century, with very slight overlap with the UCMNE archives in Record Group No. 88.
Series V, Publications, contains a small amount of material related to two UCMNE newsletters dating from 1976 to 1999.
The Photographs and Slides of Series VI are a significant addition to the earlier UCMNE archives, with photographs dating back as far as 1886. Many of the photos and slides are undated, but care has been taken to keep them together as they were handed over by the donor, so there is substantial probability that the undated photos come from the same decade as those dated ones with which they were placed. One of the photographs, taken in June, 1936, had to be placed in an oversize folder.
Series VII, Artifacts, contains items that would have been used at UCMNE conferences and events.
Arrangement
I. Organization and Policy Records, 1934 - 2000
II. Conferences and Events, 1942 - 1999
III. Related Organizations, 1920 - 1999
IV. Financial Matters, 1947 - 1998
V. Publications, 1976 - 1995
VI. Photographs and Slides, 1886 - 1999
VII. Artifacts, 1990 - 2000
College students -- Religious life; Universities and colleges -- Religion; University Christian Movement in New England
- Organization and Policy Records, 1934-2000; Series I
  - Historical documents
    - SCMNE history, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - SCMNE history, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - SCMNE history, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - SCMNE history, 1944-1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - SCMNE history, 1948-1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - SCMNE history, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - SCMNE history, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - SCMNE history, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - UCMNE history, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - UCMNE history, 1978-1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - UCMNE history, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - UCMNE history, 1993-1996 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Change of Name" official documents, 1963; 1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Dissertation on SCM in NE by Wilmer Kitchen: Part I, 1948 (Box 13, Folder 103)
    - Dissertation on SCM in NE by Wilmer Kitchen: Part II, 1948 (Box 13, Folder 104)
    - UCM's Official Display Album at conferences, 1985-2000 (Box 13, Folder 101)
    - Rev. Christine Blackburn's notebook, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 102)
  - Annual Reports
    - Annual reports, 1948-1994 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Board of Directors
    - Board of Directors' meetings, 1966-1982 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Board of Directors' meetings, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Board of Directors' meetings, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Board of Directors' meetings, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Board of Directors' meetings, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Board of Directors' meetings, 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Board of Directors' meeting, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Board of Directors' meeting, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Board of Directors' meeting, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Board of Directors' meetings, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence received, 1985-1995 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence sent, 1976-1993 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence sent, 1994-1998 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence - fundraising, 1983-1990 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence - fundraising, 1991-2000 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Evaluations and Reports
    - Evaluations and reports, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Mission Intern Program
    - Mission interns, 1980-1984 (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Conferences and Events, 1942-1999; Series II
  - 50th Anniversary Celebration, 1984 Oct
    - Mailing lists, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Invitations and publicity, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Responses from invited guests ( A - L ), 1984 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Responses from invited guests ( M - Z ), 1984 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - The Anniversary Day (audio tape included), 1984 Oct (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Acknowledgments, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Chaplain Ministry
    - Chaplain affairs, 1993-1999 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Chaplain survey, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Chaplain conference, 1999 Oct (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Conferences, Sessions, Planning Meetings
    - National Assembly of Student Christian Associations, 1942 Dec (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Program and strategy meeting at MIT, 1967 Nov (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - UCM General Committee Meeting in Washington, DC, 1969 Feb (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - UCM Annual Assembly at Michigan State University, 1969 Jun (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - "Women's Projects" - Cambridge, MA, 1971 Oct (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - SCM Seminar - Blue Ridge Assembly, Black Mountain, NC, 1975 Sep (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - "The Challenge of Justice" - Cambridge, MA, 1976 Feb (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - NE Regional Student Conference - Cambridge, MA, 1976 Oct (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - NE Regional Student Conference - Providence, RI, 1977 Nov (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - "Liberating the Bible" - East Brookfield, MA, 1978 Mar (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - "Liberating the Bible" - Boston, MA, 1978 Nov (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Summer work project - Providence, RI, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - "Faith and Commitment to Social Action" - Cambridge, MA, 1979 Oct (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - "Student Responsibility and US World Power" - Cambridge, MA, 1980 Apr (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - "Militarism and Christian Responsibility" - Framingham, MA, 1980 Oct (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - "Waging Peace" - Cambridge, MA, 1981 May (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Summer work project - Boston, MA, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Student spring retreat - Cambridge, MA, 1982 Apr (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Student planning meeting - Cambridge, MA, 1982 Jun (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Fall conference - Yale University - New Haven, CT, 1982 Nov (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - "Christian Community" - Amherst, MA, 1983 Apr (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Summer work project - Philadelphia, PA, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Conference on the Philippines - Newton Centre, MA, 1984 Apr (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - "Faith, Values and Vocation" - Groton, MA, 1984 Oct (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Fall Conference with Robert McAfee Brown - Hanover, NH, 1985 Sep (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Student tour of the Philippines, 1986 Jan (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - "Central America Week", 1986 Mar (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - "White Racism" - Boston, MA, 1986 Apr (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - "The Global Village" - Durham, NH, 1986 Nov (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Student planning meeting, 1987 Feb (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - "Thinking Globally" - Brown University, Providence, RI, 1987 Apr (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - Student retreat, 1987 Apr (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - Retreat follow-up meeting, 1987 Sep (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - "ISMs: The Invisible Influence" - Burlington, VT, 1989 Apr (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - "Creation in Crisis" - Calgary, Alberta, Canada, 1989 May (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - "Choices: Making Ethical Decisions" - Williamsburg, MA, 1989 Nov (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - "Ecology and Theology" - Spring Conference, 1990 Mar (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Student planning meeting, 1990 Jul (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - "Spirituality and Activism" - Mid-Winter Conference, 1991 Feb (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Student planning meeting - Durham, NH, 1991 Apr (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Student planning meeting - Durham, NH, 1992 Jan (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - "Spirituality and Sexuality" - Durham, NH, 1992 Mar (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - "Truth and Consequences" - Framingham, MA, 1992 Nov (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - National Ecumenical Conference: The Philippines - Cambridge, MA, 1992 Nov (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - United Ministries in Higher Education - 2nd Annual Day - Auburn, MA, 1994 May (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - National Campus Ministry Association - Michigan State University, 1994 Aug (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Elizabeth Morris Social Justice Film Series - Boston University, 1994 Feb (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - "Anti-Racism" - Fall Conference - Cambridge, MA, 1994 Nov (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Miscellaneous cultural events sponsored by UCMNE, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Lecture by Sharon Welch - University of VT, 1995 Apr (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - "Taize" - Fall Conference - Cambridge, MA, 1997 Nov (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - "Cult Awareness" Symposium, 1997 Dec (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - "Progressive Campus Ministry" - CCSU - New Britain, CT, 1998 Nov (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - Study Trip to Mexico, 1998 Dec (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - "Risking Art, Risking Faith" - Cambridge, MA, 1999 Jun (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - "American Labor Movement" - Brown University, Providence, RI, n.d. Mar (Box 7, Folder 57)
- Related Organizations, 1920-1999; Series III
  - World Student Christian Federation [WSCF]
    - WSCF affairs and events, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - WSCF affairs and events, 1981-1983 (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - WSCF affairs and events, 1987-1993 (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - WSCF affairs and events, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - WSCF Centennial project, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - WSCF affairs and events, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - WSCF: "Frequently Asked Questions" "Helen Morton", 1982-1984 (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Other Organizations
    - National Ecumenical Student Conference [NESC], 1981-1983 (Box 8, Folder 65)
    - National Interim Committee [NIC], 1981-1983 (Box 8, Folder 65)
    - Technology Christian Association, 1920-1931 (Box 8, Folder 66)
    - Young Christians for Global Justice, 1982-1983 (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - Student Christian Movement [SCM] at Yale University, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 68)
    - Student Christian Movement [SCM] of Canada, 1996-1999 (Box 8, Folder 68)
    - United Ministries in Higher Education [UMHE], 1993-1997 (Box 8, Folder 69)
    - Synod of the Northeast Presbyterian Church, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - Campus Ministers of Greater New England, 1987-1994 (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - "Appropriate" Magazine, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 72)
    - "Women and the Word", 1994 (Box 9, Folder 72)
    - Retreat sites, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 72)
- Financial Matters, 1947-1998; Series IV
  - Automotive
    - Automotive records, 1987-1988 (Box 9, Folder 73)
  - Real Estate
    - Rental agreements, 1984-1996 (Box 9, Folder 74)
  - Financial Records
    - Financial reports, 1974-1977 (Box 9, Folder 75)
    - Financial reports, 1978-1980 (Box 9, Folder 76)
    - Financial reports, 1982-1987 (Box 9, Folder 77)
    - Financial reports, 1988-1992 (Box 9, Folder 78)
    - Financial reports, 1993-1998 (Box 9, Folder 79)
  - Tax Matters
    - Exemption status, 1947-1994 (Box 9, Folder 80)
    - Deposit slips, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 81)
    - Tax reports, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 82)
    - Tax reports, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 83)
    - Tax reports, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 84)
    - Tax reports, 1978-1979 (Box 10, Folder 85)
    - Tax reports, 1988-1993 (Box 10, Folder 86)
- Publications, 1976-1995; Series V
  - Material used for newsletters, 1990-1995 (Box 10, Folder 87)
  - "Newsletter" of the University Christian Movement, New England, 1976-1986 (Box 10, Folder 88)
  - "Momentum", 1993-1995 (Box 10, Folder 89)
  - Miscellaneous, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 89)
- Photographs and Slides, 1886-1999; Series VI
  - First student conference - Northfield Mt. Hermon, MA, 1886 (Box 10, Folder 90)
  - Early photographs, n. d. (Box 10, Folder 90)
  - Silver Bay conference, 1920-1921 (Box 11, Folder 91)
  - Blairstown conferences, 1920-1930 (Box 11, Folder 91)
  - Assorted photos, 1920s (Box 11, Folder 91)
  - Kalamazoo, MI, 1930s (Box 11, Folder 91)
  - Orono, ME and Oberlin, OH, 1930s (Box 11, Folder 92)
  - O-AT-KA conference, 1937 (Box 11, Folder 92)
  - O-AT-KA conference, 1939 (Box 11, Folder 92)
  - Assorted photos, 1930s (Box 11, Folder 92)
  - Assorted photos, 1930s (Box 11, Folder 93)
  - Assorted photos, 1940s (Box 11, Folder 94)
  - Durham, NH conference, 1940s (Box 11, Folder 94)
  - CT Valley conference, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 94)
  - Assorted photos, 1947 (Box 11, Folder 94)
  - Assorted photos, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 95)
  - Leonard Clough's photos (Martha's Vineyard), 1947-1951 (Box 11, Folder 95)
  - Assorted photos, 1950s (Box 12, Folder 96)
  - Assorted photos, 1960s (Box 12, Folder 97)
  - SCM Regional Council, 1963 (Box 12, Folder 97)
  - Assorted photos, 1964 (Box 12, Folder 97)
  - O-AT-KA conference, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 97)
  - Assorted photos, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 98)
  - Opera House, Boston (?), 1983 (Box 12, Folder 98)
  - Fall conference, Dartmouth College, Hanover, NH, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 98)
  - Fall conference, Durham, NH, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 98)
  - Spring conference, Brown University, Providence, RI, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 98)
  - Easter, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 98)
  - SPPC Meeting, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 98)
  - Assorted photos, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 98)
  - Assorted photos, 1980s (Box 12, Folder 99)
  - UCM Spring conference, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 99)
  - Unnamed conference, 1999 (Box 12, Folder 99)
  - "AntiRacism" Conference, Boston, MA [slides], 1986 (Box 12, Folder 100)
  - Assorted slides [1980s?], n. d. (Box 12, Folder 100)
  - SCM Conference, Northfield, MA (Oversized photo), 1936 Jun (Box OV-d4)
- Artifacts, 1990s; Series VII
  - UCM Banner, T-Shirt, Coffee Mug and Campaign button, 1990s (Box 14, Folder 105)